what about eating plants since there are
also live organisms if we're gonna kill
a plant to eat we're going to kill an
animal to eat or is it still the
fundamental truth that we have to kill
to eat and it's all the same are we
still being specious to you know pick
killing plants over animals and I think
there's actually some core distinctions
here that are really worth making
there's an evolutionary purpose for pain
and that really the ethic that we're
looking at here is cause no harm or
cause as little harm as possible to the
point of view of a sentient experience
right shattering a rock apart if the
rock doesn't feel anything isn't an act
of violence even though there was harm
from one point of view but the rock
wasn't experiencing as far as we know
about rocks experiencing harm so when we
say cause no harm or cause the least
amount of harm possible it's two things
capable of experiencing that harm right
and so there's an evolutionary purpose
for pain which is to be able to move
away from something harmful to the
organism okay so in all animals our
sensory nerves nerves that take in
information and our motor nerves are
nerves that can then respond to that
information are intimately tied and they
actually co-evolved going up the
evolutionary ladder and so notice that
whenever there's a pain response it will
always trigger a motor response of one
of two kinds so either you touch
something hot or sharp and you move away
from it or you have a sprained ankle and
you make sure not to step on it or not
move into it but the purpose of that
pain is to protect the the organism
because of some response capacity and
that response capacity involves our
movement capacity right so this is a
place where plants and animals
fundamentally differ plants don't have
real-time movement capacity right they a
sunflower can track the Sun over the
course of a day very slowly but they
don't have the ability to move away from
something harmful or to stop moving in
some way that's harmful to them and so
there's no evolutionary purpose for pain
for them and it's important to
understand that the process of
experiencing pain it's physiologically
mediated and it requires a lot of energy
so in us the pain process is mediated
through
a acetylcholine crossing synaptic gaps
producing an opiate response you know in
adrenal and sympathetic responses
there's a lot of energy required to
experience pain and that was only
selected for because it was advantageous
that the creatures who experienced it
moved away from harm better or didn't
move into harm better so they they
actually got through reproduce better
and natural selection selected for their
ability to feel pain right when if a
tree or a plant the key to how they can
gather energy from sunlight and none of
the other animals can has to do with
their ability to be rooted and be able
to gather a huge amount of nutrition
from the soil and to be able to support
this huge base of foliage that can do
all of this photo reception right and so
because of that they give up the ability
for movement and with it there really is
no evolutionary purpose for pain
wouldn't have been selected for that's
the first thing the second thing is that
when we look in other animals we see in
their nervous system opiate receptors on
their neurons which have to do with the
chemistry of modulating the pain process
and we see that on every animal all the
way down to hinge valve creatures like
clams and they all have the same kinds
of opiate structures that you know
indicate the same kinds of pain
processes because they have an ability
to respond and the clam is kind of the
most simple one which is they can close
up if there's something potentially
harmful that means they have to
experience harm right experience
something subjectively and they can open
in response to positive stimuli or at
least a lack of negative stimuli in the
plant kingdom we don't see anything like
in opiate kind of chemistry and we don't
see anything response wise like that now
the book the secret life of plants and
you know a number of books and studies
that have been done that showed that
plants do show some kind of electrical
response to being cut or to other plants
being cut or burned in their presence
doesn't mean plants have no response
capacity but their response capacity is
very very limited relative to animals
response capacity and so the main kind
of thing is if a plant is being cut it
can't stop that from happening
cannot move away from it can't pull into
its turtle shell can't close its clam
shell can't what it can do is it can add
resins to the SAP and that
area to be able to stop the loss of sap
right and so when we see the electrical
responses galvanic responses in plants
we see that they're responding and we
can answer amorphize that and call it
plant screaming but we don't really see
any basis to to suspect that the plant
is having a subjective experience of
pain does this mean that plants have no
subjective experience at all no qualia
this is actually at the edge of our
scientific knowledge we don't know most
neuroscientists say no plants don't have
any experience some people have reason
to think that they do have experience
but we don't have any reason to think
that there's an evolutionary relevance
for them or any indication of an actual
pain or kind of suffering process
because they couldn't respond to it and
they don't show those signs so that's a
major distinction right in the in in the
process of saying hey if I'm taking a
plant life here it's still alive but am
i inducing suffering and all the
indications we have indicate no and even
if so in a radically different way right
the other thing that's worth noting is
that even if there was some pain or
suffering that the plant experienced
when we are eating animals the animals
had to eat plants and they there's some
entropy there's some energy loss in that
process so it's gonna take many pounds
of plant vegetation to produce a pound
of animal vegetation that then the
person could eat and so by supporting
the supply and demand chain of eating
that animal you're causing the harm to
the animal plus that towards however
many other plants so that there's really
kind of no water held in that argument